<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A briefe declaration for vvhat manner of speciall nusance concerning private dwelling houses, a man may have his remedy by assise, or other action as the case requires Vnfolded in the arguments, and opinions of foure famous sages of the common law; together with the power, and extent of customes in cities, townes, and corporations, concerning the same: together with the determination of the law, concerning the commodity, and use of houses, and their appurtenances. Whereunto is added, the iustices of assise their opinion, concerning statute law for parishes, and the power of iustices of peace, church wardens, and constables; and to know what they are to doe concerning bastards borne in their parishes, reliefe of the poore, and providing for poore children, what remedy for the same.</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1636</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 67 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 25 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-04">2011-04 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A73793</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 6453.5</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S109443</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99845090</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99845090</idno>
            <idno type="VID">150572</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A73793)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 150572)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 1269:13, 1955:05)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A briefe declaration for vvhat manner of speciall nusance concerning private dwelling houses, a man may have his remedy by assise, or other action as the case requires Vnfolded in the arguments, and opinions of foure famous sages of the common law; together with the power, and extent of customes in cities, townes, and corporations, concerning the same: together with the determination of the law, concerning the commodity, and use of houses, and their appurtenances. Whereunto is added, the iustices of assise their opinion, concerning statute law for parishes, and the power of iustices of peace, church wardens, and constables; and to know what they are to doe concerning bastards borne in their parishes, reliefe of the poore, and providing for poore children, what remedy for the same.</title>
                  <author>Monson, Robert, d. 1583.</author>
                  <author>Plowden, Edmund, 1518-1585.</author>
                  <author>Wray, Christopher, Sir, 1524-1592.</author>
                  <author>Manwood, John, d. 1610.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[2], 45, [1] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed [by Bernard Alsop and Thomas Fawcet] for William Cooke, and are to be sold at his shop, neere Furnivals-Inne gate in Holbourne,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1636.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>The "four famous sages" are Robert Monson, Edmund Plowden, Sir Christopher Wray, and John Manwood.</note>
                  <note>Printers' names from STC.</note>
                  <note>In this edition the text begins on B2r.</note>
                  <note>Identified as STC 6453 on UMI microfilm reel 1269.</note>
                  <note>Reproductions of the original in the Henry E. Huntington Library and Art Gallery.</note>
                  <note>Appears at reel 1269 and at reel 1955 (same copy filmed twice).</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Nuisances --  Great Britain --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Parishes --  Great Britain --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Illegitimacy --  Great Britain --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Poor laws --  Great Britain --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2010-01</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-01</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-03</date>
            <label>Ali Jakobson</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-03</date>
            <label>Ali Jakobson</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-04</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:150572:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>A Briefe DECLARATION <hi>For</hi> VVhat manner of ſpeciall Nuſance concerning private dwelling Houſes, a man may have his remedy Aſſiſe, or other Action as the Caſe requires.</p>
            <p>Vnfolded in the Arguments, and opinions of foure famous Sages of the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon Law; together with the power, and extent of cuſtomes in Cities, Townes, and Corporations, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning the ſame: together with the determi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation of the Law, concerning the commodity, and uſe of Houſes, and their appurtenances.</p>
            <p>Whereunto is added, <hi>The Iuſtices of Aſſiſe their Opinion, concerning ſtatute law for Pariſhes, and the power of Iuſtices of Peace, Churchwardens, and Conſtables; and to know what they are to doe concerning Baſtards borne in their Pariſhes, reliefe of the Poore, and providing for poore Children, what remedy for the ſame.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed for WILLIAM COOKE, and are to be ſold at his ſhop, neere <hi>Furnivals</hi>-Inne gate in <hi>Holbourne.</hi> 1636.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="declaration">
            <pb facs="tcp:150572:2"/>
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:150572:2"/>
            <head>The Arguments, and opinions of foure famous Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges of the Common Law touching the power, and extent of cuſtomes of Cities, Townes, Corporati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, and Inheritances, together with the deter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mination of the Law concerning the commodity, and uſe of Houſes with their appurtenances, and wherein an action may be maintaineable concer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning the ſame, and wherein not.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">A</seg> Man hath a houſe,<note place="margin">Mr. <hi>Mounſons</hi> argument.</note> and the windows thereof open into an others mans houſe, whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther hee may build a houſe, ſo as to ſtoppe up the ſame lights, or not: concerning which, I purpoſe to ſhew you my opinion, and likewiſe to ſhew unto you the neceſſity and uſe of Houſes.</p>
            <p>The firſt, and chiefe uſe of an houſe is to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fend man from the extremity of the winde, and weather. And by the receit of comfortable light, and wholſome ayre, into the ſame to pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerve mans body in health.</p>
            <p>Therefore who ſo taketh from man ſo great a commodity as that which preſerveth mans health in his caſtle, or houſe, doth in a man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:150572:3"/>as great wrong as if he deſeiſed him al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>together of his Free-hold.</p>
            <p>As if I have a Mill, and another will turne away the water running to the ſame, I may bring an Aſſiſe againſt him.</p>
            <p>So, if I have a Pipe, which conveyeth water unto my houſe through the ground of another man, and he will cut my pipe, I ſhall have an action againſt him: In like manner who ſo ſtoppeth my light, is the cauſe that no ayre can enter into my houſe, without which no man can live, and a houſe lacking light, is rather a dun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geon then a houſe.</p>
            <p>If one who hath a horrible ſickneſſe be in my houſe, and will not depart, an action will lye againſt him, and yet he taketh not any aire from me, but infecteth that which I have.</p>
            <p>So if one caſt filth neere unto my houſe, I may bring my action againſt him. If a man build ſo high that his houſe droppeth on my houſe, I ſhall have remedy againſt him.</p>
            <p>And though light and ayre be common, yet if by any mans owne act they may bee made private, they may not then bee taken from him, and if they be, he ſhall not bee without remedy.</p>
            <p>This appeareth by Hawkes, and Deere, which be <hi>feraenaturae,</hi> yet if by mans induſtry they are made tame, the owner will thereby gaine pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perty in them: but peradventure it will bee ſayd, The ſoyle is his owne, and it is <hi>Damnum
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:150572:3"/>abſ<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan> injuria,</hi> what then? Though it be his owne, he muſt ſo uſe it, that hee hurt not his Neigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bour.</p>
            <p>As if a man had a Pond of water, and will ſuffer it to drowne his neighbours land, he ſhall have remedy againſt him.</p>
            <p>If a man be bound to repaire the bankes of the ſea that it drowne not the land adjoyning, and ſo doth not, but the land is drowned; an action lyeth againſt him. You may perhaps ſay there is plenty of light remaining, this not<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>withſtanding our action will lye very well, for the taking away, or impayring part thereof. As an action was brought <hi>quare arctavit,</hi> and 2. <hi>H.</hi> 4. where a man had a way and another plowed the ſame, and it was thought there that an action would very well lie, and yet the way remained. If I have common in your Land, and you will plough part of the ſame Land, I ſhall very well maintaine an action againſt you. So it is of Common of Eſtovers, and piſcary: And yet in all theſe caſes, the whole is not gone, but ſome part remaineth. This proveth that though he hath not ſtopped the whole light of the houſe, yet for that he hath ſtopped parcell, an action is very well maintainable, but if you had ſaid, that on the ſame ſide there had beene plen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty of light, it might have better ſtood with reaſon.</p>
            <p>As touching your cuſtome, whereby a man may ſtoppe his neighbours lights: I thinke this
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:150572:4"/>is rather <hi>Malus uſus,</hi> then any cuſtome: for as I have learned of M<hi rend="sup">r</hi>. <hi>Hales,</hi> a cuſtome is thus defined, <hi>Conſuetudo eſt jus non ſcriptum nunquam repugnans rationi naturali,</hi> and therefore if any cuſtome ſwerve from reaſon, and naturall equi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, it is but <hi>malus uſus;</hi> and for that to bee aboli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhed, for by entendment, and conſideration of the law, and reaſon, every cuſtome had a reaſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nable beginning, as that caſe in 35. H. 6. of ſel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling Iewels in Cheapſide may have a reaſona<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble beginning. In like manner the cuſtome of <hi>Gavelkinde,</hi> that Sonnes ſhall equally inherit the Lands of their Fathers. Such is the cuſtome, that if a woman marrie without licence, that ſhe ſhall looſe her dowrie.</p>
            <p>So is it alſo of the cuſtome that one towne may enter Common with another. All theſe, and ſuch like may well bee thought to have a reaſonable beginning.</p>
            <p>Otherwiſe it is, where by intendment their beginning cannot be thought reaſonable.</p>
            <p>As that a man ſhall pay reliefe, when that hee ſhall marry his daughter. And as the cuſtome is in Mich. 35. H. 6. fol. 31. of the pledging of goods: So it is of the cuſtome, to arreſt a man before the day of payment. In like ſort in 2. H. 4. that the tenant ſhall not put his beaſts in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the Common, before the Lord hath put in his, which peradventure hee will never doe, ſo it is 10. H. 6. If the Major of a towne will preſcribe to impound all beaſts which ſhall bee
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:150572:4"/>dammage feſonet in his owne pound, and there to keepe them till he bee ſatisfied as he liſt, or if he preſcribe to uſe, and occupie the ſame beaſts howſoever he pleaſeth.</p>
            <p>In 2. R. 3. and 22. E. 4. one demanded whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther it were a good cuſtome, that if the Mayor of a towne ſuſpect a man, that hee may arreſt and impriſon him 3. dayes: this was thought no good cuſtome, but to be moſt abhorring, and diſſonant from reaſon. And therefore foraſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>much as houſes bee neceſſary, and cannot bee without light, and ayre, their beginning was lawfull, neceſſary, and reaſonable, but that a man might ſtoppe up his neighbours lights, was never neceſſary, neyther had lawfull, or rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſonable beginning, neyther at any time obtained the force of a law, or cuſtome, for in K. <hi>Henry</hi> the 2. his time, it was but a conſtitution in <hi>London,</hi> and not any cuſtome, or law; and therefore ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver allowed, or confirmed by Parliament, for <hi>Magna Charta Ca.</hi> 9. did confirme ſuch old li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berties and cuſtomes as <hi>London</hi> had at that time: And therefore, if this were not any law or cuſtome at the time of the making of that ſtatute, it neyther was nor could bee confirmed by the ſame, for the more generall Statutes ſhall have a reaſonable conſtruction. As the Statute that doth prohibite maintenance, ſhall have a conſtruction, for lawfull maintenance is not thereby prohibited. The like law is that where it is ſayd, that a fine ſhall bee a Barre to a <hi>feme
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:150572:5"/>coverte,</hi> this is to be underſtood of a good, and lawfull fine, ſo this confirmation by Parliament of cuſtomes, and liberties of <hi>London,</hi> ſhall bee intended a confirmation of all their good, and lawfull cuſtomes, and not of unreaſonable, or wrongfull uſage, ſuch as in 27. <hi>H.</hi> 6. if the houſe of tenant for terme of yeeres decay, that then he ſhall pay no rent, &amp;c. But if your cuſtome were then good, and ſo confirmed by Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, yet the words thereof may not bee ſtretched to our caſe, the words are <hi>viſus fene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrarum,</hi> and the Civill law ſayth, a man may <hi>eſtop viſum,</hi> and not <hi>lumen, lumen eſt deſcendens de coelo, viſus eſt meus proſpectus ad terram.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And our Law ſayth, <hi>petit viſum terrae,</hi> And <hi>viſus</hi> and <hi>lumen</hi> differ. But Sir you cannot in this caſe defend your ſelfe both by the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon law and cuſtome too. For you ought ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolutely to truſt to the one of them, and if you had plead thus by way of Barre, your plea with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out all doubt would have beene double.</p>
            <p>As if a man will pleade affeafement with war<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>renty, and rely not on the warrenty, this plea is double. So in the caſe at the Barre, you plead both the common Law, and the cuſtome, and your plea is double, and therefore for all theſe cauſes I thinke the plaintiffe ought to recover.</p>
            <p>Mr. <hi>Plowden.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Albeit it hath beene alleaged,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Mr.</hi> Plowdens Argument.</note> that the win<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dowes
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:150572:5"/>have beene time out of memory there, and the lights ancient, it is all one, as if the houſe had beene built at this day. Put the caſe there is a pale betwixt your ground and mine, and you build to the uttermoſt part of mine, by your firſt building I am bridled and ſtopt of my building; And in the Country who ſo ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keth a hedge, will make a dike in the uttermoſt part upon his owne land. So hee that maketh a Parke, will leave ground out of the ſame com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paſſe without the pale for this Keeper to walke about it, for there hee may better heare if any body bee there within, then if he were within himſelfe, And this is called free-bownd. If a man build his houſe ſo high that it droppeth on mine, an action will very well lye, for there is a manifeſt hurt, and wrong done unto me: but 22. H. 6. where the <hi>Prior</hi> of St. <hi>Edees</hi> had three Mills, an other man built an other by them, hee could not have any remedy for this. But if any of his tenants which held of him by grinding at his Mill grinde at the new Mill, the <hi>Prior</hi> may have an action againſt him, for hee whoſe the land is, might uſe the ſame for his greateſt commodity, and gaine.</p>
            <p>If a man cut downe Trees which fall upon an other mans land, hee ſhall have his action; otherwiſe it is, if a Tree fall by reaſon of winde. So in our caſe: of our owne ſoyle we may make the beſt, as in 12. H. 8. a man had a pond, and let the ſame runne out, whereby the next dwellers
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:150572:6"/>land was drowned, this was but <hi>damnum abſ<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan> injuria,</hi> wherefore no action would lie. In 4. E. 3. a man had a Lime kilne, which deſtroyed the Fruit of his neighbour, who maintained his action, for in that caſe this taketh place, <hi>Sic. utere, tuo, ut alienum non laedas;</hi> And Mr. <hi>Raſtall</hi> ſayth in his booke, if a man have a Dye-houſe, and the water which runneth to his houſe, kil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leth the Fiſh of another, an action lyeth. If a man caſt filth under my walls, I may puniſh him for it. And in the 46. <hi>E.</hi> 3. The <hi>Prior</hi> of <hi>Buckhurſt</hi> had a ſluice, whereby Salmons came in, and one ſtopped the ſame, wherefore hee had his action. Like whereas one cutteth away the water, which runneth to my Mill, for the proofe whereof Mr. <hi>Reynolds</hi> put a caſe out of 19. <hi>E.</hi> 3. where an Aſſiſe was brought for two things, one be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe hee had levied a houſe to ſtop the light; an other, becauſe he could not repaire the ſame: There it was thought that no action would lye, becauſe hee might have remedied, this in the be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginning when hee built his houſe. And the caſe was in 7. <hi>Edw.</hi> 3. in the laſt poynt, and there the Lawyer ſayd, that hee might have left ſpace enough in his owne Land, and the party was non-ſuted. <hi>Horwoods</hi> report hath two verſes,
<q>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Saepe recordare ſi debes adificare</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Vt poteris ſtare cum cam vis reparare.</hi>
                  </l>
               </q>
            </p>
            <p>But you ayde your ſelfe with a preſcription
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:150572:6"/>that you have had light time out of minde, this is no good preſcription, for a preſcription muſt be againſt ſome party. But this is againſt God; You ſay further, that the other had no houſe, which is not good, for a preſcription muſt be in the affirmative, and this is in the negative, and ſo ſayth <hi>Priſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>t</hi> in 22. H. 6. that a man cannot pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcribe in the not having a houſe. But admitting it to be the uſage.</p>
            <p>An uſage is generall, and a conſtitution ſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciall in 12. E. 4. A diverſity is taken between u<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſage, and cuſtome, for that a cuſtome is a thing diſagreeing from the Common law, but not con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary, &amp; alſo it would not be beautifull that Ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties ſhould have any voyd places, in them, and it would be moſt honourable that they ſhould be populous. And therefore was there a Statute made 27. H. 8. <hi>caprim<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>,</hi> that there ſhould not be any voyd places in divers Citties, alſo houſes are neceſſary for the ſuſtenance of man, in 22. E. 4. there is a cuſtome that if a man plough his Land, hee might turne his plough upon an other mans land: and this was thought a good cuſtome for the favour of Tillage, much more our caſe of Building is to bee favoured. 8. E. 4. the cuſtome is, that a Fiſh-man may drive ſtakes into an other mans ground to drie his Nets, which was allowed for a very good cuſtome. Likewiſe 15. E. 2. one preſcribed that when the Hay was carryed out of a certaine Medow, that he ſhould occupie the land until our <hi>Lady</hi> day, which was allowed by the Court. So a man
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:150572:7"/>may preſcribe to have Common of eſtovers in another mans Land, and to cut them down him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe. The Lord in ancient demeſme preſcribed, that if the villaine of another Lord remained a yeere and a day in ancient demeſme, that then it ſhall not bee lawfull for his Lord to take him from thence. In like manner, one may preſcribe to have gravell in my Land, and all theſe cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtomes ſtand very well with reaſon. If I have a way, and another man plow up the ſame, I can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not have an action on my caſe, but I muſt have an Aſſiſe and to is the booke in 2. H. 4. Mr. <hi>Fleet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wood</hi> ſayth that all cuſtomes muſt ſtand with rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon. And in 5. E. 4. it is ſayd, that albeit all cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtomes are confirmed, yet they muſt be exami<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned, by the rule of reaſon, as the cuſtome of <hi>Ga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>velkinde</hi> ſtandeth with reaſon. The Statute that giveth a writ of raviſhment, <hi>de Gurd</hi> to <hi>Guarden</hi> in ſoccage ſhall bee extended to the Mayor, and Aldermen of <hi>London,</hi> to give them like remedy which was confirmed by 1. E. 3. Alſo the Sta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tute that no man ſhall give lands in Mortamaine, yet Citizens and Freemen of <hi>London</hi> may give lands in Mortmaine by their cuſtome, which cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtome is alſo confirmed by act of Parliament. As for the doubleneſſe of the plea I will not ſay any thing, for that it is not any Iuſtification, but onely for to diminiſh the damages, if perhaps it bee found againſt us. And therefore upon the whole matter, I thinke the plaintiffe ought not to recover in this action. I thinke the contrary, and firſt I will conſider theſe foure things.</p>
            <list>
               <pb n="11" facs="tcp:150572:7"/>
               <item>Firſt, whether ſuch buildings, <hi>ex oppoſito,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Mr. <hi>Wrayes</hi> Argument.</note> be a nuſance by the Common law.</item>
               <item>Secondly, whether this cuſtome be a good cuſtome.</item>
               <item>Thirdly, whether ſuch kinde of buildings be for the beautifying of the City.</item>
               <item>Fourthly, whether the ſayd confirmation by Parliament make this cuſtome good, or not.</item>
            </list>
            <p>As touching the firſt matter, the nuſance which is ſuppoſed to be in ſtopping up of win<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dowes in the South part of an houſe, I conceive is a nuſance by the Common law, for by the Common law, one ſhall not hurt the Freehold of another, and no greater hurt, grievance, or dammage can be done to any mans Freehold, then to take away the light and ayre thereof, which is comfortable, &amp; commodious for him, for when this light, and ayre are taken from him, his houſe remaineth as a dungeon. And divers caſes there bee where a man taketh a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way from another not the thing it ſelfe, but the commodity of the thing, and for that he ſhall have his remedy by action: as if I have a water running through your ground unto my Mill, and you will turne away the courſe there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of, or ſtop the ſame; I may bring an aſſiſe 9. <hi>E.</hi> 3. <hi>pla.</hi> 19. yet I will confeſſe, that if another build a Mill by my Mill, I may not have any action, as 22. <hi>H.</hi> 6. for it is <hi>damnum abſque injuria.</hi> So it is in 2. <hi>H.</hi> 4. in the caſe of the Schoole <hi>cadem ratio.</hi> But if any ought to grinde at my
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:150572:8"/>Mill, and another will hinder them, an acti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on lyeth 9. <hi>H.</hi> 6. <hi>fo.</hi> 45. where the <hi>Pryer</hi> of St. <hi>Bartall</hi> had a Faire, and one interrupted the commers thereto, whereby his Toll was impai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red, and yet not his Fayre, but the profit of his Fayre taken away, and hee had remedy. So in our caſe he hath not medled with our Freehold, and yet hath he hurt our Freehold. So in 4. <hi>E.</hi> 2.13. <hi>E.</hi> 3. If I have a Fayre, and the King will grant another, if my Fayre bee impaired by this I ſhall have an action, and ſo of a Ferry, and the reaſon is, becauſe a man is compella<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble to maintaine his Fayre, Ferry, or Market, and if he doe not, it is puniſhable in a Leete. But of a Schoole, otherwiſe it is, for that a man is not bound to maintaine it, but Houſes in Cities men are bound to maintaine, and that by Statute, otherwiſe they may in curre the puniſhment. 18. <hi>E.</hi> 3. one built his houſe ſo high over mine, that the raine dropped from his up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on mine, and it was thought there that an acti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on was maintainable, yet that hurt might have beene amended <hi>à fortiori</hi> in our caſe where the hurt is perpetuall, and cannot be amended. And if for a way an action lyeth, as it is in the 42 <hi>E.</hi> 3. much more for an hurt to our health, which above all things men have regard unto, for the proofe whereof we have a writ in the Regiſter <hi>de leproſo amovendo.</hi> Likewiſe the ſelling of corrupt meate, whereby mens bodies may ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtaine harme, is puniſhable in a Leete, which
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:150572:8"/>proveth that the Common law hath regard un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the health, and welfare of every private man. There is a caſe in 4. <hi>E.</hi> 3. <hi>lib. aſſ. pla</hi> 3. where one built a Lime-kilne, and his neighbour was anoy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed by the ſmoke thereof, and had his remedy. If a man ſhall be puniſhed for ſmoke, which may be avoyded, and dureth but at times, what ſhall we thinke of the taking away of light, and ayre, which cannot be amended, but remaineth a con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinuall and perpetuall nuſance? as for the caſes in 19. <hi>E.</hi> 3. which hath bin avouched ſo oft to make ſtrongly againſt us, I take them to be one caſe, for ſo much as the Iuſtices which ſpeake in one place, ſpeake alſo in the other place; and laſt of all in both caſes, the caſe was thus, an aſſiſe of nu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſance was brought, and the Plaintiffe counted how the defendant had levied a houſe, ſo that thereby his light was ſtopped up, and that hee could not ſo well come to his houſe as he did be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore, alſo that he could not repaire his houſe ſo well as he could before.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Herebe</hi> ſaid, as to the light be it a nuſance, ſuch a one as it is. <hi>Tiel. quel.</hi> for the repayring none, for when a man buildeth, he muſt leave ſo much ſpace on his owne ground that he may come to repaire his houſe, and if hee had thought that ſtoping of his light had bin no nuſance he would not have ſaid, be it a nuſance <hi>Tiel quel.</hi> but have ſaid as he did to the other caſe of repayring, it is no nuſance. And therfore for the firſt matter, I thinke this to be a nuſance by the Co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mon law.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="14" facs="tcp:150572:9"/>As touching the ſecond matter, whether this cuſtome be a good cuſtome or not, and I thinke the ſame is no good cuſtome: For <hi>conſuetudo eſt in &amp;c. ut ſupra,</hi> a cuſtome is not againſt law, and reaſon, but this cuſtome of yours is againſt reaſon, and is in effect, as if a man ſhould take my life from me, for theſe bee the inſtruments to maintaine, and preſerve mans life, and the law ſayth, <hi>ſic utere tuo, ut alienum non laedas,</hi> there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore a cuſtome againſt this precept, is <hi>malus uſus,</hi> and therefore <hi>abolendus,</hi> as the caſe in 21. <hi>E.</hi> 4. It the Kings Bayliffe or any other Bayliffe di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtraine Cattell, and bring them to the Lords Pound, and if the owner did not within three dayes agree with the Lord, that then he ſhould looſe bis Cattell, this was thought unreaſonable and not allowed for any good cuſtome. So in 9. <hi>H.</hi> 6. where there the Lord of a Leet would have preſcribed to have all the waſte ground, but hee could not, becauſe it was againſt reaſon, that he who had nothing in the Land ſhould have the waſts. Like unto the ſayd caſe in the 35. <hi>H.</hi> 6. <hi>fo.</hi> 31. of pledging of goods, and ſuch is that caſe in 43. <hi>E.</hi> 3. where the Lord of the Ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>nor would have preſcribed, that none of his Tenants ſhould marry their daughters without his licence; this cuſtome was thought to bee againſt all equity, and reaſon. In 13 <hi>E.</hi> 3. in a <hi>dum fuit infra aetatem,</hi> one would have preſcribed, that if the Plaintiffe could number 12 <hi>d.</hi> he might <hi>alien</hi> his land by the cuſtome: this is not a reaſonable cuſtome,
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:150572:9"/>for a man may be able to number 12<hi>d.</hi> and yet not have diſcretion enough to alien his Land. So it is likewiſe againſt naturall reaſon, that one ſhould barre me of my light, and ayre, without which I cannot live, and therefore theſe things be of neceſſity. Alſo it is againſt the Law that one ſhould meddle with the Freehold of ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther man, unleſſe it be for a Common-wealth, as 8. <hi>E.</hi> 4. where one juſtified the ſetting in of ſtakes for to drie his nets, and likewiſe in the 11. <hi>H.</hi> 2. where one brought an action for taking or driving his Hogges, the Defendant juſtified, becauſe the cuſtome of the City was, that if any mans Hogges came into the City, and upon warning given to the owners to keepe them out: if they came againe, that then they ſhall be forfeited. This is a reaſonable cuſtome, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe Swine are beaſts that may cauſe diſeaſes to bee in a City, and therefore it is againſt the Common-wealth, in 22. <hi>E.</hi> 4. Where it is ſayd; that a man may turne his plow upon another mans land, that is a good cuſtome, for by this meanes no land ſhall be unſowne, which is for the maintenance of Tillage, and the benefit of the Common-wealth. But this your cuſtome is but a private cuſtome, and not for the mainte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance of the Common-wealth, and therefore is like unto the cuſtome in 43. <hi>E.</hi> 3. that if the te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant ceaſe to doe his cuſtome, the Lord may enter, this cuſtome ſtandeth not with the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon law, neither with the Statute which put<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teth
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:150572:10"/>the Lord to his <hi>ceſſavit,</hi> and giveth him not any entry. So it is to bee thought of the cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtome in 2. H. 4. that the Tenants ſhall not put their beaſts into the Common before the Lord hath put in his, which peradventure hee will never doe, ſo that the Tenants ſhall never have their Common. So it is if a man preſcribe that the alienation of the Husband of the Lands of his Wife ſhall bee good without examination of her. Like law of the Cuſtome in 43. <hi>E.</hi> 3. that if any goods bee wayned in any manner, and if any man take them, that then it ſhall bee lawfull for me to diſtraine, and detaine the di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtreſſe untill ſuch time as I am ſatisfied: by theſe caſes rehearſed it is manifeſt, and cleare that all uſages againſt naturall reaſon, and the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon law of this Realme, are not cuſtomes, but evill uſages, and not to be allowed. So in our caſe a cuſtome to take away a mans light, and ayre, preſervers of health, muſt needs be <hi>malus uſus,</hi> and therefore ought to bee taken away; For good uſages ſtand with reaſon, and as <hi>Bracton</hi> ſayth, muſt give place to reaſon, and law. But you will ſay, that the Law of your City is ſuch: I ſay, if it ſtand not with reaſon, and law, it ſhall not bee allowed. As 10. <hi>E.</hi> 3. in an ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peale brought by a Citizen, the defendant waged battaile, the Citizen ſaid the cuſtome of <hi>London</hi> is ſuch, that a ſtranger ſhould not wage battaile againſt a Citizen, this was thought no good cuſtome, nor ſufficient to deprive a man
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:150572:10"/>of a benefit, which the law giveth him. And ſo in 27. <hi>H.</hi> 6. in an action of debt upon a leaſe for yeeres, the defendant ſayd that the cuſtome was, that the plaintiffe ſhould repayre the hou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes, and if not, that the defendant ſhould pay no rent, this was thought to bee no cuſtome allowable. For the third point, this is no beauti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fying at all to the City. In our caſe Mr. <hi>Hayles</hi> his houſe is an ancient houſe, and therefore a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt reaſon that by latter building, the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>modity, and uſe of the ſame ſhould bee taken away. You ſay alſo that it is a thing honourable to have buildings in Cities; This I grant, and I thinke no man will deny it: but by building of one, to impaire a better houſe, this is not any beautifying, or honour at all to a City, but rather the contrary. For the fourth matter, if the cuſtome be not good, the confirmation can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not make it good: for as I take the law, the common learning is, that a confirmation cannot make a voide thing good: as for a confirmation <hi>eſt firmum facere id quod non firmum fuit ante, ſed fuit tamen</hi> 26. H. 8. If an Infant grant an advou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon, and at his full age confirmeth the ſame, by this confirmation nothing is wrought. So it is in the caſe of 33. <hi>E.</hi> 3. where the leaſe for yeeres was made by a Biſhop, and he dyed before the yeeres expired, the ſucceſſour confirmeth the ſaid leaſe, and <hi>nihiloperatur.</hi> Likewiſe in 39. H. 6. the King granted an advouſon to one, and after granted the Mannor with the advouſon to
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:150572:11"/>another, and after the confirmation is made, yet the advouſon paſſeth not. But where the Statute limitteth, that men may deviſe unto corporations in Mortemaine, yet if they will deviſe to any that is not a Corporation, it is without warrant: And alſo albeit a man may not wage his law in <hi>London,</hi> yet if at the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon law, an action be brought againſt him, hee may: So it is of the caſe in 20. H. 6. that if one be brought before the Sheriffe, that the Mayor may diſmiſſe him, yet after judgement hee may not diſmiſſe him.</p>
            <p>Likewiſe 12. E. 4. where one would have preſcribed to buy things without paying of tolle, that he could not be allowed. And there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore I will conclude that ſuch cuſtomes as ſtand with law, and reaſon, are to bee allowed, and contrary ſuch as ſwerve from the rules of law, and reaſon, to be diſallowed. As this cuſtome of yours, that a man ſhould ſtop his neighbours lights is altogether unlawfull, and unreaſonable, and therefore the plaintiffe ought not thereby to bee barred of his action.</p>
            <p>Mr. <hi>Manwood.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Mr.</hi> Manwoods Argument.</note>Here be two matters chiefly to bee conſide<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red, whether by the Common law this bee a nuſance, to ſtop up part of a mans light, then if the Common law ſeeme to be doubtfull, whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther the cuſtome will helpe us, or not, divers
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:150572:11"/>caſes have beene put, when a man toucheth not the Free-hold of another, but on his owne land doth wrong unto another mans. But all theſe caſes doe vary from our caſe, for they are where a man hath a private profit in a thing, and another by doing an act upon his owne land taketh away the ſame, wherefore an action will lie, as the caſe in 46 <hi>Edw.</hi> 3. where the Abbot of <hi>Buckhurſt</hi> had Salmons, coming in at ſluice from the Sea, and a ſtranger ſtopped the ſame, ſo that they could not come, and hee had his action. So it is where one taketh away my way, becauſe this is a thing locall. And ſo if water running to my Mill, if one miſcarry the ſame: generally whereſoever I have a private profit, or intereſt, and one barre mee of the ſame, it is injury: but the ayre is not any element locall, neyther may any man miſcarry it, for it ſuffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reth nothing to be voyd, alſo light, and ayre be not things of neceſſity, but of pleaſure, and be not any profit in <hi>certo loco,</hi> and therefore not like unto other caſes of things both profitable, and alſo neceſſary. The caſe of the Ferrie I will grant, that if I have a Ferrie to tranſport men, and another will erect another I ſhall have an action, becauſe that I am compellable to main<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine it, and the not keeping of it, is preſent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able in a Leete. The ſame Law is of the Market, where the King granteth another Market <hi>ad nocumentum</hi> of mine, I may have a <hi>Scire-facias</hi> to repeale his letters patents if he have theſe words
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:150572:12"/>in them, that the grant ſhould not bee to the hurt, or prejudice of any other market; and if not, I ſhall have an action on my caſe: your caſe was alſo compared to the caſe in 4. <hi>E.</hi> 3. and 4. <hi>aſſ. pla.</hi> 3. where the <hi>aſſ.</hi> was maintained, not for that the plaintiffe was annoyed by the ſmell of the ſmoke, but becauſe his Apple-trees, and other his fruits were deſtroyed by the ſame, and this is a good reaſon, for that it is to his diſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>heritance. As for the caſe of the Lime-houſe at <hi>Ratcliffe,</hi> and the ſmoke of Smiths houſes which caſt many unſavoury ſmels, it is <hi>damnum abſ<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan> injuria.</hi> And I my ſelfe was by a Smith annoyed by the ſmell of his ſmoke, but yet might I not have any action againſt him. In 18. <hi>Edw.</hi> 3. one built an houſe ſo high that it dropped from his to mine, in this caſe an action will lye, for my tyles are thereby conſumed, <hi>gutta cavat lapi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dem.</hi> So of the caſe in 2. H. 5. if by common aſſent our Houſes joyne and a gutter is made betwixt us, if I plucke up my part, you may maintaine an action againſt mee. All theſe caſes hitherto put, have beene of taking away a locall commodity, or elſe of conſuming ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing.</p>
            <p>The caſe of the filth I finde not in my booke, but in the booke of Entries, and there it was <hi>Per parietes,</hi> ſo that the walls were hurt thereby. But I will agree with you, that if all your win<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dowes were ſtopped, that an action will lie, and where you ſay <hi>fit utere tuo ut alienum non laed as,</hi>
               <pb n="21" facs="tcp:150572:12"/>this is not meant of things of pleaſure, but of things of profit. And here is not any part of your houſe conſumed, but herein a let of your pleaſure onely, for which your action is not maintaineable. And if I have a Windmill, and another will build another by mine, I cannot have any action againſt him, 11. H. 4.7. E. 3.22. H. 6. But otherwiſe it is of a Water-milne, 9. <hi>aſſiſar. pla.</hi> 19. where one had a Watermill, and another built neere unto him, ſo that hee could not grinde ſo much as hee was wont, in this caſe a man may very well mainetaine his action. If I have an Inne, and another ſet another in the ſame Towne, hee is not puniſhable, but if hee will ſtop my gueſſe, which come to my houſe, I ſhall have remedy. If I have a Brew-houſe, and another build another by mine, I ſhall have no action. 12. H. 8. If water fall on my land, and I make a Sluice, and let it out of my land unto another mans; this is diſpuniſhable, for every man may doe this one after another un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>till it come unto the River, but if it be a river, otherwiſe it is; For there it is in <hi>loco certo.</hi> If one houſe ſhould not bee adjoyning unto another, it would bee a great deformity, and if <hi>Cheap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſide</hi> were ſo built, it would be a ſtrange <hi>Cheap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſide.</hi> And the Civill lawes ſay, that two lights on the former part, and backe of an houſe, are ſufficient. And if you make your windowes in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to our garden, this is a wrong done unto us, for by this meanes I cannot talke with my friends
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:150572:13"/>in my Garden but your ſervant may ſee what I doe, and ſo the wrong firſt begun in Mr. <hi>Hales.</hi> And therefore <hi>Vim vi repellere licet.</hi> And <hi>I S</hi> hath not conſumed, or hurt any part of his houſe, but interrupted him of his pleaſure onely. But I further affirme, that for every hurt a man may not have an action, but if a man be oftentimes hurt, he may very well have an action. As if the Lord diſtraineth for rent, an action lyeth not, but if he diſtraine ſo oft, that I cannot plow my land, I ſhall have an aſſiſe. So the Kings grant of exemption to one is good, but if it bee to di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vers, it is not good. But if the Common law would not helpe us, yet cuſtome will, &amp; where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>as it hath beene ſayd, that it is againſt naturall reaſon, and law, it is not ſo, <hi>Conſuetudo ex ratio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nabili cauſa privat communem legem,</hi> and unleſſe it doe <hi>privare communem legem,</hi> it is no cuſtome. As that an Infant of 15 yeeres age, may aline. For at this age he may conſent to marriage, therefore in as great reaſon may he alien his lands; and in ſome places any Infant of 9 veeres may binde himſelfe apprentize, which is a good cuſtome and ſtandeth with reaſon. But ſome cuſtomes there are that be not good, As that the tennants ſhall not drive their Beaſts into the Common before the Lord hath put in his. So if the leſſe will preſcribe to ſurrender at his will, 7. <hi>H.</hi> 6. otherwiſe it is of the cuſtome in the 14. <hi>H.</hi> 4, that the Tennant ſhall not alien without the preſentment of the ſame before, this is a good
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:150572:13"/>cuſtome, and yet againſt common reaſon, but yet if it hath any taſte or ſmatch of reaſon, it ſhall be allowed. As if the Lord preſcribe that the tennant ſhall not Common with any beaſts, but thoſe which were bred on the ſame land, this is good, for this will cauſe the tennant to breed Cattell; likewiſe that a <hi>female ſole Merchante</hi> ſhall ſue without her husband, this is good, and yet againſt Common law, and reaſon, becauſe the husband hereby is diſcharged of all ſuch buſines: therefore if a cuſtome have any part of reaſon, it ſhall be allowed. As 8. <hi>E.</hi> 3. that a man may make an eſtate to his wife during her life, and that ſhould bee as good as an endow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment <hi>ad oſtium eccleſia.</hi> So is it of the cuſtome of the <hi>Iſle of Man,</hi> that to ſteale a Capon, or a Pigge, ſhall bee Felony, and not to ſteale a Horſe, or Cow, for that the one may bee hid, the other may not. Likewiſe is it, that the youngeſt ſonne ſhall inherit, becauſe hee is leſſe able to helpe himſelfe. So is it of the cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtome of <hi>Kent,</hi> The Father to the bough, the ſonne to the plow, and yet directly againſt the Common law. So I thinke of the caſe of Hogs put by Mr. <hi>Wray,</hi> for that in the time of peſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lence it is dangerous to let them come into Citties.</p>
            <p>This Citty is the greateſt Citty, and moſt po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pulous in this Realme, and the more populous the more honourable, &amp; the more buildings, the more populous and honourable will it be. And
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:150572:14"/>therefore Building is to bee favoured. And by this building all his light is not ſtopped, but parcell. And Mr. <hi>Hales</hi> thereby looſeth no not any great commodity, but is reſtrained of a lit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle pleaſure, for which hee cannot maintaine his action.</p>
            <p>To the act of Parliament I will ſpeake no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing, but this I will ſay, that if any cuſtome bee meerly voyd of reaſon, it is not good. As the cuſtome in 5. H. 7. that if the Lord diſtraine the beaſts of his tenants for rent, that hee may detaine them until hee be ſatisfied at his plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure; and 21. H. 7. that if any doe breake the Pound he ſhall pay 3 l. this is a voyd, and unrea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſonable cuſtome to binde an eſtranger, and yet by common conſent of the Lord, and tennants, it is good to binde the tenants.</p>
            <p>So if I preſcribe, that if any mans Sheepe goe on my ground all the day, to have the foldage of them in the night, is a good cuſtome, becauſe by common entendment the owner hath <hi>quid pro quo.</hi> So our cuſtome is for the maintenance of the Citty, neyther is it againſt the common law directly, neither hereby any offence, or hurt is done unto Mr. <hi>Hales,</hi> for his Houſe is not thereby impayred. And therefore, I thinke his action will not lye.</p>
            <trailer>Finis de cenx Arguments.</trailer>
         </div>
         <div type="resolutions">
            <pb n="25" facs="tcp:150572:14"/>
            <head>Reſolutions of the <hi>Judges of Aſsiſes,</hi> 1633.</head>
            <p n="1">1. <hi>Queſtion.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">W</seg>Hether the Church-wardens, and Over-ſeers of the poore of a Pariſh with aſſent of two Iuſtices of the Peace, one beeing of the Quorum, may by the Statute of 43. <hi>Elizabeth, cap.</hi> 2. or any law enforce a Pariſhioner of the ſame Pariſh to take a Childe of a poore pariſhioner of the ſame pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſh, who is not able to keepe his ſayd childe, to be an apprentiſe?</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Reſol.</hi> The Statute of 43. of <hi>Elizabeth,</hi> which ſayth, that the Church-wardens and over-ſeers of the pariſh ſhall put out Children to bee ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prentices, neceſſarily implyeth, that ſuch as are fit muſt receive Apprentices, and the putting out of poore Children to be apprentices is one
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:150572:15"/>of the beſt wayes for the providing for the poore.</p>
            <p n="2">2. Q. If they may, then whether they muſt not give money with him, and who ſhall deter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mine what money ſhall bee given with him, if the party that is to take ſuch an apprentice, and the Church-wardens, and Overſeers cannot agree thereupon?</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Reſol.</hi> There is no neceſſity that money muſt be given, but that muſt be left to the diſcreti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of the Church-wardens, and Overſeers, all circumſtances of age and ability, beeing conſidered, and if they cannot agree with the party, then the Iuſtices of Peace neere adjoyning, or in their default the Seſſions of peace are to determine theſe Controver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſies.</p>
            <p n="3">3. Q. Whether a Knight, Gentleman, Cler<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gy-man, or Yeoman, or one that is Sojour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner, uſing husbandry, cloathing, or graſing, or the like, may be enforced to take ſuch an ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prentice?</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Reſol.</hi> Every man who is by calling or pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſion or manner of living, that entertai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neth, and muſt have the uſe of other ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vants of the like quality, muſt entertaine ſuch apprentices, wherein diſcretion muſt bee given upon due conſideration of circumſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces.</p>
            <p n="4">4 Q. Whether a wealthy man keeping few or no ſervants, nor wanting a ſervant, but li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:150572:15"/>privately may be enforced to take ſuch an apprentice; if not, then whether hee may bee taxed towards the putting forth of ſuch an ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prentice?</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Reſol.</hi> For the receiving of ſuch apprenti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, the anſwer may bee referred to the que<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtion next before; but out of doubt every ſuch perſon muſt contribute to the charge, as to other charges for the proviſion for the poore.</p>
            <p n="5">5. Qu. Whether they may enforce a pariſhio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner that is of one pariſh, to take ſuch a childe, apprentice, that is of another pariſh, but with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in the ſame County or diviſion, if the proper pariſh be not able to provide for the children of the ſame pariſh?</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Reſol.</hi> The Iuſtices may provide Maſters for them in other pariſhes within the ſame hundred; if the ſame hundred be not able, then out of that hundred in the reſt of that County; As for other proviſion for the poore, which muſt bee at a quarter Seſſions.</p>
            <p n="6">6. Q. If ſuch a Pariſhioner may be enforced to take ſuch an apprentice, and ſhall refuſe not onely to take ſuch an apprentice; but alſo re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fuſe to be bound to appeare at the next quar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter Seſſions, or Aſſizes, what ſhall be done to him?</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Reſol.</hi> If any refuſe; let ſuch a one bee bound over to the next Seſſions or Aſſizes; if he re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fuſe to give ſuch bond, let him bee ſent to
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:150572:16"/>the <hi>Gaole,</hi> there to remaine until hee will give ſuch bond.</p>
            <p n="7">7. Q. If ſuch a Pariſhioner who refuſeth to take ſuch an apprentice ſhall bee bound over to the Seſſions for not taking ſuch an apprentice, and when hee appeareth there, ſhall likewiſe refuſe, what ſhall bee done to him, and what ſhall bee done to the Parents who refuſe to ſuffer their Children to bee put out to bee ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prentices, themſelves not being able to main<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine them?</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Reſol.</hi> If at the Seſſions or Aſſizes ſuch a one refuſeth to take an apprentice and his excuſe be not allowed, it is fit he bee bound to the good behaviour, and it will be a good courſe to indict ſuch a refuſer for a contempt, and thereupon to fine &amp; impriſon him; if he refuſe to be bound to the good behaviour, let him be impriſoned un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>till he will; &amp; the Kings book of orders directs that ſuch bee bound with good ſureties to ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peare at the Councell board; &amp; if the Parents of ſuch poore children refuſe to ſuffer their chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren to be bound apprentices, or being bound, entice them away, themſelves not beeing able to maintaine them, let them bee committed to the houſe of correction.</p>
            <p n="8">8. Q. Whether it be in the power of any ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerall quarter Seſſions to mitigate any penalty upon a Statute law; If the party indicted ſhall ſubmit himſelfe to the fine of the Court, and waive the traverſe?</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="29" facs="tcp:150572:16"/>
               <hi>Reſol.</hi> If the party be convicted or confeſſe the fault, it is not in the Power of the Court to mitigate the fine, in ſuch cafes where the Statute makes it certaine: but if the party in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dicted proteſting his Innocencie, yet <hi>quia no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>luit plitare cum domino Rege</hi> puts himſelfe up into the grace of the Court, the Court may im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe a moderate fine, and order to forbeare the proſecution.</p>
            <p n="9">9. Qu. If any be bound to appeare at the Seſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſions, and ſhall tender ſubmiſſion to the Court, whether the Seſſions may ſtay the indictment, and mitigate the fine aforeſayd upon the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſion of the fact?</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Reſol.</hi> This is anſwered before to the next precedent Article.</p>
            <p n="10">10 Q. If a man be convicted for being drunk, tipling, and keeping an unlicenſed Alehouſe, or being licenced, for ſuffering others to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maine tipling in his houſe, or for ſwearing or driving Cattell upon the Sunday contrary to the Statute in that caſe provided: whether the Iuſtice of Peace, before whom hee was con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>victed, or any other Iuſtice of the Peace may diſcharge him of all or part of the Forfei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture or puniſhment appoynted by the Sta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tute?</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Reſol.</hi> The Iuſtices have no ſuch power of mitigation after conviction, where the Sta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tute appoynts the meaſure of the puniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment.</p>
            <p n="11">
               <pb n="30" facs="tcp:150572:17"/>11. Qu. Whether a Conſtable may upon a warrant for carrying one to the houſe of cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rection for keeping an unlicenced Alehouſe upon the ſecond conviction, breake open the houſe wherein the party convicted is, to appre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hend him?</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Reſol.</hi> This queſtion is to be adviſed upon, it is put in generall termes and referred to bee conſidered in the particular where it appea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reth.</p>
            <p n="12">12. Qu. If a woman unmarried be hired from weeke to weeke, or from halfe yeere to halfe yeere, in one Pariſh, and there is gotten with child, and then goeth from thence unto another pariſh, where ſhe is ſetled in ſervice by the ſpace of two or three moneths, and then diſcovered that ſhe is with childe: The queſtion is, whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther ſhee ſhall be ſetled in the Pariſh where ſhe was begotten with childe, or in the Pariſh where ſhe was laſt ſetled?</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Reſol.</hi> The place where ſuch a woman was lawfully ſetled, is the direction in this caſe, not where ſhe was begotten with child.</p>
            <p n="13">13. Qu. If a woman-ſervant unmarried bee begotten with child, and then goeth out of her Miſtris ſervice, before or after it is diſcovered that ſhe is with child, and the reputed father be runne away, or is not able to free the Pariſh: whether the Maſter may be enforced to pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vide for her till ſhee bee delivered, and for a moneth after?</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="31" facs="tcp:150572:17"/>
               <hi>Reſol.</hi> If the Maſter hath legally diſchar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged his houſe of ſuch a ſervant, hee is no more bound to provide for her then any o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther.</p>
            <p n="14">14. Qu. In caſe a Pariſh conſiſt part of anci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent <hi>Demeaſne,</hi> and part of <hi>Guildable,</hi> an Aſſize is made for the reliefe of the maihemed Souldiers, the Gaole, &amp;c. according to the Statute of 24. <hi>Elizabeth, cap.</hi> 2. whether the tennants in ancient demeſne ſhall contribute with the Guildable for the payment of the Aſſize?</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Reſol.</hi> The Statute doth not diſtinguiſh be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tweene the ancient Demeaſne and the Guildable in theſe caſes, <hi>ubi lex non diſtinguitur, ibi nec nos diſtinguimus.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="15">15. <hi>Q.</hi> Whether an Indictment of forceable detainer bee within the Statute of 1. <hi>Iacobi, cap.</hi> 5. and not to be removed by <hi>Certiorari,</hi> unleſſe the partie Indicted firſt finde ſureties accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to that Statute, and whether the party In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dicted bee to be bound in his abſence to proſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cute according to that Statute, and whether an Indictment of forcible entry, &amp;c. found at a private Seſſions bee to be removed by <hi>Certio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rari</hi> without ſureties, according to that Sta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tute?</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Reſol.</hi> This is fitteſt to be left unto the Court of Kings-bench, to whoſe Commiſſion, and ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſdiction this is moſt proper.</p>
            <p n="16">16. <hi>Q.</hi> If one be convicted upon the Statute of 3. <hi>Car. R. cap.</hi> 13. for driving of Cattell
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:150572:18"/>on the Sunday through ſeverall pariſhes; whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther hee ſhall forfeit 20. s. to every of the ſayd Pariſhes; or onely to one; if to one, then to which of them?</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Reſol.</hi> This Statute giveth the Forfeiture but of one 20. s. for one Sabbath day. Although the driving on that day bee through divers Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſhes. Therefore where the action is firſt at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tached, and the diſtreſſe firſt taken, that pariſh ſhall have the benefit of the Forfeiture, and not the other.</p>
            <p n="17">17. Qu. If one who is under the age of 30. yeeres, and brought up in Husbandry, or a mayd ſervant, or brought up in any of the arts or trades mentioned in the Statute of 5. <hi>Elizab. c.</hi> 4. and not enable according to that Statute, to live at his or her owne hand, ſhall bee war<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned by two Iuſtices of the Peace to put him or her ſelfe in ſervice by a day preſcribed by them, and ſhall not doe the ſame accordingly, but ſhall after continue living at his or her owne hand, what courſe ſhall bee taken with ſuch a perſon, and how puniſhed?</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Reſol.</hi> Such perſons being out of ſervice, and not having viſible meanes of their owne, to maintaine themſelves without their labour, and refuſing to ſerve as an hyred ſervant, by the yeere, may be bound over to the next Seſſions or Aſſizes, and to be of the good behaviour in the meane time, or may be ſent to the houſe of correction.</p>
            <p n="18">
               <pb n="33" facs="tcp:150572:18"/>18. Qu. Whether the taxe for the reliefe of the poore, upon the Statute of 43. <hi>Elizabeth,</hi> ſhall bee made by ability or occupation of lands, or both, and whether the viſible abi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lity in the pariſh where hee lives; or gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall ability whereſoever, and whether his rent received, within the Pariſh where hee lives ſhall bee accompted viſible ability, and whether hee ſhall bee taxed of them onely and for any Rents received from other Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſhioners: and what ſhall bee ſayed viſible a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bility? <hi>Reſol.</hi> The Land within each pariſh is to be taxed to the charges in the firſt place equally and indifferently, but there may bee an additi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on for the perſonall viſible ability of the pari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhioner within that Pariſh according to good diſcretion, wherein if there be any miſtaking, the Seſſions, &amp;c. or the Iuſtice muſt judge be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tweene them.</p>
            <p n="19">19. Q. Whether ſhops, ſalt-pits, ſheds, pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fits of a Market, &amp;c. bee taxable to the poore as well as lands, Cole-mynes, &amp;c. expreſſed in the Statute 43. <hi>Elizabeth?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Reſol.</hi> All things which are reall, and a yeerely Revenue, muſt be taxed to the poore.</p>
            <p n="20">20. Q. Whether the taxe for the County ſtocke, Gaole, and houſe of Correction is to bee made by the Statute of 14. <hi>Elizabeth, cap.</hi> 43. <hi>Elizabeth:</hi> by ability, and upon the In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>habitants of the pariſh onely, or upon
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:150572:19"/>them, or the occupiers of Lands, dwelling in that pariſh: or whether ſuch as occupy lands in that pariſh, and dwell in another pariſh ſhall be taxed?</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Reſol.</hi> If the Statute in particular cafes give no ſpeciall direction, it is good diſcretion to goe according to the rate of taxation for the poore: but when the Statutes themſelves give directions, follow that.</p>
            <p n="21">21. Q. Whether any taxes ought to be made for the charges that petty Conſtables and Bor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhoulders are at in conveying rogues from pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſh to pariſh, and relieving of them and how to be rated?</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Reſol.</hi> It is fit to relieve the Conſtable and Tything-men, in ſuch ſort as it hath beene uſed in the ſeverall places where they live.</p>
            <p n="22">22. Qu. Whether a Iuſtice of Peace may diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>charge a ſervant being with childe from her ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vice, allowing that as a reaſonable cauſe that ſhe is thereby made unable to doe the ſervice which otherwiſe ſhe might have done, and if hee may diſcharge her, whether that Pariſh ſhall provide for her, till her delivery, if ſhe cannot provide for her ſelfe: and ſo alſo if her time be expired before her delivery, who ſhall provide for her after her time ended?</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Reſol.</hi> If a woman being with childe procure her ſelfe to bee retayned with a Maſter who knoweth nothing thereof, is a good cauſe to diſcharge her from his ſervice. And if ſhee bee
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:150572:19"/>begotten with childe during her ſervice, it is all one, but the Maſter in neyther caſe muſt turne away ſuch a ſervant of his owne authority. But if her terme be ended, or ſhee lawfully diſchar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged; the Maſter is not bound to provide for her, but it is a misfortune falne upon the pariſh, which they muſt beare, as in other caſes of ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſuall impotency.</p>
            <p n="23">23. Qu. Whether being delivered for a ba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtard childe in one pariſh, and goeth into ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther with her childe; and becomes vagrant, and ſo is ſent to the place of her birth: her baſtard childe being under the age of 7. yeeres, ſhall bee ſetled with the mother, and there main<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tained, if the mother be not able, nor the repu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted Father knowne, found: or whether it ſhall be ſent to the place of its birth, or being ſetled with the mother, whether the Pariſh where it was borne, ſhall be ordered by the two next Iu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtices to pay a weekly ſumme towards the main<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tenance of it?</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Reſol.</hi> The Baſtard childe muſt bee placed with the mother, ſo long as it is within the quality or condition of a Nurſe childe, which ſhall bee, till ſeven yeeres of age; and then it is fit to be ſent to the place of its birth to bee provided for, the mother or reputed father, not being able. And the Pariſh where the childe is borne ſhall not be forced to contribute to the charge, as long as the Mother lives, and the child be under 7. yeeres old.</p>
            <p n="24">
               <pb n="36" facs="tcp:150572:20"/>24. <hi>Q.</hi> A man with his Wife and Children takes an houſe in one Pariſh, for a yeere: and before the end of his terme is unlawfully put out of poſſeſſion, and after taketh part of an houſe, as an Inmate in another Pariſh, from whence hee is alſo put out, and then not beeing able to get any dwelling, they come to lye in a Barne in a third Pariſh where the Husband falleth ſicke, and the Wife is delivered of a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nother childe, where ought theſe to bee ſet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led?</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Reſol.</hi> If a man or woman having houſe or habitation in one pariſh be thruſt out, this is an illegall unſetling which the Law forbiddeth, for none muſt bee enforced to turne vagrant, and ſuch one muſt bee returned to the place where hee or ſhee was laſt lawfully ſetled, and the Childe alſo borne in the time of this diſtracti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on.</p>
            <p n="25">25. Q<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> Whether an apprentice put out by the Churchwardens, &amp;c. according to the Sta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tute to a Maſter in another Pariſh, if his Maſter dye and leave no Executor or Adminiſtrator fit to keepe an apprentice or able to place him: Hee ſhall bee provided for in the pariſh where hee was apprentice or ſhall bee ſent backe to the pariſh from whence hee was put out?</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Reſol.</hi> Servants and apprentices are by law ſetled in that pariſh, and if they become impo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tent there, the pariſh muſt abide the adven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:150572:20"/>after their terme or time of ſervice be law<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully ended.</p>
            <p n="26">26. Q. What is accompted a lawfull ſetling in a pariſh, and what not?</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Reſol.</hi> This is too generall a queſtion to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive a perfect anſwer to every particular caſe which may happen: but generally this is to bee obſerved, that the law unſetleth none who are lawfully ſetled; nor, permits it to be done by practice, or compulſion, and every one who is ſetled is a native houſholder, ſojourner, an ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prentice or ſervant for a moneth at the leaſt, without a juſt complaint made to remove him or her, ſhall be held to be ſetled.</p>
            <p n="27">27. Qu. A rogue is taken at C. and will not confeſſe the place of his birth: neyther doth it appeare otherwiſe but that hee confeſſeth the laſt place of his habitation to be at S. hereupon he is whipped and ſent to S. at his comming to S. the place of his birth is there knowne by ſome to be at W. and thereupon the rogue confeſſeth it to be ſo: whether he might without any new vagrancy be ſent to W?</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Reſol.</hi> In this caſe it is fit to ſent ſuch a rogue to the place of his birth: for this is but a miſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king and no legall ſetling.</p>
            <p n="28">28. <hi>Q.</hi> If an Indictment be preferred to the grand Iury of the quarter Seſſions of the peace againſt one for murther, manſlaughter, for robe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry, felony, or Petilarceny, and ignoramus found thereupon, whether the ſaid Seſſions may deliver the party by Proclamation or not?</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="38" facs="tcp:150572:21"/>
               <hi>Reſol.</hi> Not by Proclamation at all, but for petty Lacenyes, and other petty Fello<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nies; in diſcretion the Gaole may be delivered of them.</p>
            <p n="29">29. Q. If a Conſtable be choſen and refuſeth to take his Oath, what ſhall be done, and whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther a Conſtable may make a deputy, and by what meanes?</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Reſol.</hi> The refuſall or neglect to take oath in ſuch a caſe is a contempt worthy of puniſhment, and thereupon to fine, and impriſon him, and the making of a deputy is rather by toleration, then by law.</p>
            <p n="30">30. Qu. If a Conſtable dye or remove out of the pariſh where, &amp;c. How is his place to be ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plyed?</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Reſol.</hi> By the Lord of the Leete, if that time fall neere, otherwiſe by the Seſſions; but if that bee too farre off, then by the next Iuſtices:</p>
            <p n="31">31. Q. If a poore weake man be choſen Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtable or Tything-man, and bee unfit for the place, how may hee be removed, and a fit man ſworne in his roome?</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Reſol.</hi> The Iuſtices of Peace muſt helpe this, and if the Lord of the Leete have po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wer to chooſe a Conſtable or Tything-man and performe ſo ill, it is a juſt cauſe to ſeize his liberty.</p>
            <p n="32">32. Qu. If a Nurſe-childe, a Scholler at a Grammar-ſchoole, or in the Vniverſity prove
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:150572:21"/>to be impotent by Sickneſſe, lameneſſe, lunacy, or diſcovery of Ideocy, &amp;c. how ſuch perſons ſhall be diſpoſed?</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Reſol.</hi> A Nurſe-childe, or a Scholler at the Grammar-ſchoole, or at the Vniverſity, or per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons ſent to the Common gaole, Hoſpitall, or houſes of Correction, are not to bee eſteemed as perſons to be ſetled there, more then Travai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lers in their Innes, but their ſetling is where their Parents are ſetled, and Children borne in common Gaoles, and Houſe of correction, their parents being priſoners, are to be maintai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned at the charge of the County.</p>
            <p n="33">33. Qu. What proportion Parſonages, or Tithes ſhall beare to the taxation of the poore of the pariſh?</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Reſol.</hi> The Parſon or Vicar preſentative, ſhall according to the reaſonable value of his Parſonage, having conſideration to the juſt de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ductions.</p>
            <p n="34">34. Qu. Whether for the placing the poore of the pariſh, not to bee remove by conſent of the pariſh, theſe poore men may not bee placed as Inmates for a time?</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Reſol.</hi> They may by expreſſe words of the Statute of the 43. of <hi>Elizabeth.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="35">35. Qu. If a pariſhioner or owner within a pariſh do bring into the pariſh without the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent of the Pariſh, a ſtranger of another pariſh, which is, or apparantly is like to bee burthen-ſome unto the pariſh, how they may eaſe them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves?</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="40" facs="tcp:150572:22"/>
               <hi>Reſol.</hi> By taxing ſuch a one to the charge of the rates of the poore, not onely having reſpect to his ability or the land he occupies, but accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to the dammage and danger he bringeth to the pariſh by his folly.</p>
            <p n="36">36. Qu. For warding in the day-time, for ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prehending of Rogues, whether the Conſtable may not enlarge it to a farther time?</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Reſol.</hi> Warding in the day-time is of great uſe, and muſt bee left to the diſcretion of the Conſtables or direction of the Iuſtices to vary according to the occaſion.</p>
            <p n="37">37. Qu. Whether Alehouſes ought to bee al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowed only in thorow-fare Townes, and others in other places to bee reſtrained onely to ſell to the poore out of doores.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Reſol.</hi> The Iuſtices ſhall doe very well to allow none but in places very fit for theyr ſcituation and uſes, and to moderate the num<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber.</p>
            <p n="38">38. Q. A man for his quality otherwiſe fit to be a Conſtable, or of other Office of that nature, procures himſelfe to bee the Kings ſervant ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>traordinary, and by that meanes would excuſe himſelfe to ſerve in the Country?</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Reſol.</hi> A ſervant extraordinary may well performe his ordinary ſervice in the Countrey according to his quality.</p>
            <div type="part">
               <pb n="41" facs="tcp:150572:22"/>
               <head>The Iuſtices opinion touching the Commiſſions by which the Iuſtices ſit at Newgate.</head>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">Anciently felo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nies included all treſpaſſes, therefore the Iuſtices of Gaole delivery have power to hold plea of treſpaſſes a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt them in priſon or upon bayle to ren<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der themſelves.</note>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>HE Iuſtices at Newgate ſit by vertue of two Commiſſions <hi>(viz.)</hi> Gaole delivery and Oyer, and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terminer.</p>
               <p>By the Commiſſion of Gaole delivery they may try all priſoners in the Gaole or by B<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>yle, or ſuch as bee indicted will render themſelves, generally for all Felonies: and al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo for ſuch other offences as are particularly aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſigned to them by Statute.</p>
               <p>The Statute of 4. <hi>Elizabeth</hi> 3. <hi>cap.</hi> 2. doth give them power to receive Indictments a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt Priſoners or ſuch as are upon bayle,<note place="margin">v. 1. <hi>Mar. Dyer,</hi> 99. Iuſtices of Gaole delivery hold pleas of all appeales of felony or murder againſt one in priſon by their gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall Com: and of appeales: ſo by the ſame reaſon to take Indictments.</note> and to proceed to try the ſame <hi>(viz.)</hi> Indictments taken before the Iuſtices of the peace, and by equity thereof all Indictments before coro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners, 3. <hi>Mar. Bro. Commiſſion. omnium.</hi> 24. ſayth, That the Commiſſion is <hi>ad deliberand. Gaol. de priſon. in eiſdem exiſten.</hi> But they cannot take Indictments as Iuſtices of Gaole delivery, but being Iuſtices of the peace, they may take In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dictments againſt priſoners, but not againſt them that bee at large, for aſmuch as power
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:150572:23"/>is given them, conſequently they muſt have meanes to doe ſo, which is by Indictments, <hi>Id quarend.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Howſoever it is cleere, that they may enquire of many offences and take Indictments in ſuch caſes where power by the Statute is given to the Iuſtices of Gaole delivery, in ſuch caſes where they have authority by Law or Statute there the tytle of Indictments is, that <hi>Ad gao<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lam deliberationem tent.</hi> before the Commiſſio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners of Gaole delivery, <hi>I. S.</hi> was indicted, and the record muſt be made up ſo.</p>
               <p>And whereas by the Statute of 4. <hi>Eliz.</hi> 3. <hi>cap.</hi> 2. Indictments taken before Iuſtices of peace or Coroners, or any other againſt any Priſoners, then the entry of the Indictments is returned taken, <hi>Memorand quod ad generalem Seſſionem tent.</hi> before <hi>A, B, C,</hi> &amp;c. Iuſtices <hi>ad pacem in Com. Middleſex</hi> or <hi>London, I. S.</hi> was in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dicted, and then tryed before Iuſtices of Gaole delivery, and by vertue of the ſayd Statute, In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dictments taken before Iuſtices of the peace of <hi>London</hi> or <hi>Middleſex,</hi> are tryed before the Iuſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces of Gaole delivery.</p>
               <p>The Commiſſioner of Oyer and Terminer is <hi>Ad triand. inquirend. audiend. &amp; determinand.</hi> They may enquire of all offences mentioned in the Commiſſion, albeit the offendors bee at large, but they cannot try Priſoners upon In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dictments taken before any other then them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves, as the Iuſtices of Gaole delivery may by
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:150572:23"/>the aforeſayd Statute, unleſſe there bee a ſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciall Commiſſion made, as it was in the caſe of the Earle of <hi>Leiceſter,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">3. Mar. Bro. Com. 24.</note> mentioned in <hi>Plow. Com.</hi> for the ordinary Commiſſion of Oyer, and terminer is <hi>ad inquirend. audiend. &amp; determinand.</hi> therefore they cannot determine of things unleſſe they made enquirie firſt, and on the other ſide alſo the Iuſtices of Gaole delivery may try Indictments taken before Iuſtices of the peace, yet if one indicted before Commiſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>oners of Oyer and Terminer, the Iuſtices of Gaole delivery cannot try the ſame, becauſe the Record of the Commiſſion of Oyer and Terminer are to bee returned in the Kings Bench, 44. E. 3.31.</p>
               <p>The Commiſſion and the Records of the proceedings before the Iuſtices of Gaole deli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verie, are to bee returned to the Cuſtos Rotu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lor. of the County, when the ſame perſons are Iuſtices of Gaole delivery, and of Oyer and Terminer, they may ſit the ſame day and place, and enquire by the ſame Iurie, but the entry of the Records muſt be ſeverall, according as the Indictment is.</p>
               <p>At the Aſſiſes in the Countrey, the Iuſtices have their ſeverall power as the Iuſtices of Gaole delivery, Oyer and Terminer, and Iuſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces of the peace.</p>
               <p>But when the Records are made up, they muſt bee according to the power they made ele<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction to proceed upon.</p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="44" facs="tcp:150572:24"/>This is the regular and legall courſe. But the Clerkes of the Aſſizes promiſcuouſly make entry thereof, But if a Writ of Error bee brought, they muſt certifie according to Law, or elſe it will bee erronious, and ſo upon a <hi>Certiorari.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The Seſſions of <hi>London</hi> may bee begun at the Guild-hall, and then adjourned to New<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gate, if ſome Indictments bee at Guild-hall, then thoſe muſt bee ſo certified: if others at Newgate, then the adjournment muſt bee mentioned, and that the Indictment was then taken.</p>
               <p>Note that the tryall of Indictments taken before Iuſtices of the peace of London, can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not bee tryed at Newgate, as in nature of a tryall before Iuſtices of the peace at London, for many of the Commiſſioners, for Gaole de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>livery, are not Iuſtices of the peace for Lon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>don, but in ſuch caſes the tryall muſt be before the Iuſtices of Gaole delivery: as upon In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dictments taken before the Iuſtices of the peace of London; as in the caſe of Indictments ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken before the Iuſtices of the peace of Mid<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dleſex.</p>
               <p>But if Indictments at Newgate be original<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly taken before them, as Iuſtices of Gaole de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>livery, then it is inquirable how the Iurie ſworne, and impannelled to enquire at the Seſſions of the peace of London, or Middle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſex, doe ſerve to preſent Indictments before
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:150572:24"/>the Iuſtices of Gaole delivery at Newgate, un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſſe the cuſtome and uſage will warrant, the two ſeverall Iuries, ſworne at the Seſſions of the peace for London, or Middleſex, are alſo by the ſame oath and impannelling to ſerve for the grand Iury for the Commiſſion of Gaole deli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>very, and Oyer, and Terminer.</p>
               <p>Vpon conference with Mr. <hi>Keeling,</hi> and the Clerkes for Newgate of London, and Middleſex, and the Clerkes of Aſſizes, and view of the ſeverall Entries, a more ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture and certaine reſolution may bee given, this being in haſt, and without ſuch conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derations as were requiſite.</p>
            </div>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
            <pb facs="tcp:150572:25" rendition="simple:additions"/>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
